this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
SE radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
today I'm talking to David Kramer he's
the founder and CTO of Sentry David
welcome to software engineering radio
thanks for having me excited for today's
conversation I think the first thing we
could start with is defining what Sentry
is I know some people refer to it as an
error tracker some people have referred
to it as an application performance
monitoring tool I wonder if you could
kind of describe in your words what it
is
you know as somebody who doesn't work in
marketing I just tell it how it is so
Century started out doing error
monitoring which you know depending on
who you talk to you might just think of
as logging right like that's the honest
truth that is just logging just a
different shape or form these days it's
hard to not classify us as just an APM
tool that's like the industry that
exists it's like the tools people
understand so I would just say it's an
APM tool right we do a bunch of things
within that space and maybe it's not you
know item for item the same as say a
product like New Relic but a lot of the
overlaps there so it's like errors
performance which is like latency and
sort of throughput and then we have some
stuff that just goes a little bit deeper
within that the the one thing I would
say that is different for US versus a
lot of these tools is we
actually only do application monitoring
so we don't do any since like systems or
infrastructure monitoring meaning Sentry
is not going to tell you when you need
to replace a hard drive or even that you
need new like more disk space or
something like that because it's just
it's a domain that we don't think is
relevant for sort of our customers and
product
for people who aren't familiar with the
term application performance monitoring
what is that compared to just air
tracking the way I always reason about
it this is what I tell new hires and
what I would tell like my mother if I
had to explain what I do is like you
load Uber and it crashes we all know
that's bad right that's error monitoring
we capture the crash report we send it
to developers you load Uber and it's a
30 second spinner like a loading
indicator
as a customer same outcome for me I
assume the app is broken right so we
also know that's bad but that's
different than a crash okay Central
captures that same incentive developers
lastly the third example we use which is
a little bit more I think untraditional
but our non-traditional rather you load
the Uber app and it's like a blank
screen or there's no button to like log
in or something like this so it's kind
of like a it's broken but it maybe isn't
airing and it's not like a slow thing
right same outcome it's probably a bug
of some sorts like it's what an end user
would describe it as a bug so for me APM
just translates to there are bugs user
perceived bugs in your application and
we're able to Monitor and help the
software teams sort of prioritize and
resolve those those concerns
earlier you're talking about actual
crashes and then your second case is
maybe more of if the app is running
slowly then that's not necessarily a
crash but it's still something that an
APM would monitor yeah yeah and I think
to be fair 8 PM historically it's not a
very meaningful term like I as a when I
was more of just an individual
contributor I would associate 8 pm to
like there's a dashboard that will tell
me what's slow in my application which
it does and that is kind of core to APM
but it would also none of the
traditional tools pre-century would
actually tell you why it's broken like
when there's an error a crash it was
like most of those tools were kind of
useless and I don't know I do actually
know but I'm going to pretend I don't
know about most people and just say for
myself but most of the time my problems
are errors they are not like it's fast
or slow you know and so we just think of
it as like it's a holistic thing to say
when I've changed the application and
something's broken or it's a bug you
know what is that bug how do we help
people fix it and that comes from a lot
of different like data signals and
things like that the end result is still
the same you either are going to fix it
or it's not important and you ignore it
I don't know so it's a pretty
straightforward premise for us but again
most companies in the space like the
traditional companies when you grow a
big company what happens is like you
build one thing and then you build lots
of check boxes to sell more things and
so I think a lot of the APM vendors like
they've created a lot of different
products like rum is a good example of
another acronym that lives with an APM
and I would tell you rum is completely
meaningless it stands for real user
monitoring and so I'm like well what's
not real about monitoring the
application well nothing's not real but
like they created a new category because
that's how marketing engines work and
that new category is more like analytics
than it is like application Telemetry
and it's only because they couldn't
collect the application Telemetry at the
time and so there's just a lot of fluff
I would say but at the end of the day
too like developers or engineering teams
it's like new version of the application
you broke something let's tell you about
it so you can fix it and so earlier you
were saying how this is a kind of
logging but there's also other companies
other products that are considered like
logging infrastructure like I would
think of companies like paper Trail or
log tail so what space does Century fill
that's different than that kind of
logging so the way I always think about
it and this is personally true and what
I advise other folks is
when you're building something new when
you start from zero right you can often
take Century put it in and that's good
enough you don't even need performance
monitoring you just need like errors
right like you're just causing bugs all
the time and you could do that with
logging but like the Delta between air
monitoring login is nine Day from a user
experience like air monitoring for us or
what we built at the very least
Aggregates the errors it helps you
understand the frequency it helps you
when they're new versus old it really
gives you a lot of detail where logs
don't and so you don't need logging
often and I will tell you today at
Century Engineers do not use logs for
the most part I had a debate with one of
our team members about it like why does
he use logs recently but you should not
need them because logs serve a different
purpose like if you have traces which
tell you like like fast and slow and a
bunch of other network data and you have
this sort of crash report collection or
error monitoring thing logs become like
a compliance or an audit Trail or like a
security forensics tool and there's just
not a lot of value that you'd get out of
them otherwise like once in a while
maybe there's like some weird obscure
use case but generally speaking you can
just pretend that you don't need logs
most days and to me that's like an
evolution of the industry and so when
when century was getting started most
people were still logs and if you go
talk to SRE teams they're like oh login
is what we know some of that's changed a
little bit but but at the end of the day
they should only be needed for more
complicated audit Trails because they're
just not a good solution to the problem
it's just freeform data structured or
not doesn't really matter it's not
aggregated it's not something that you
can really use and it's why whenever you
see logging tools not even the Paper
Trails of the world but the bigger ones
like Splunk or cabana it's like this
weird what we describe is Choose Your
Own Adventure like go have fun build
your dashboards and try to make the logs
useful kind of story whereas like
something like Sentry it's just like why
would you waste any time trying to build
dashboards when we can just tell you
when something new is broken like that's
the ideal situation so it sounds like
maybe the distinction is with a more
General logging tool like you mentioned
Splunk and kibana it's a collection of
all this information
of things happening even though
nothing's necessarily wrong whereas
century is it's going to log things but
it's only going to log things if Sentry
believes something is wrong either
because of a crash or because of some
kind of performance issue yeah I would
say it's about like actionability right
like nobody wants to spend their time
digging through logs digging through
dashboards metrics are another good
example of this like just charts with
metrics on them yeah they tell me
something's happening if there's lots of
log statements they tell me something's
going on but they're not they're not
optimized to like help me solve a
problem right and so our philosophy was
always like we haven't necessarily
nailed this in all cases for what it's
worth but it was like the goal is we
identify an actual problem like close to
like a root cause kind of problem and we
escalate that up and that's it versus
asking somebody to like go have to like
build these dashboards build these
things figure out what data matters and
all this because most software looks
exactly the same like if you have a web
service it doesn't matter what language
it's written in it doesn't matter how
different you think your architecture is
from somebody else's they're all the
same it's like you've got a request
you've got a database you've got some
cash you've got all these like no known
quantity things and the slowness comes
from the same places the errors come
from the same places they're all
exhibiting the same kinds of behavior so
login is very unstructured and what I
mean by that is like there's no schema
like you can hypothetically like make it
Json and everybody does that but it's
still unstructured whereas like errors
it's it's a tight schema it's like
there's a type of error there's a
message for the air there's a stack
Trace there's all these things that you
know right and as soon as you know and
you define those things you can just
build better products and so distributed
tracing is similar hypothetically it's a
little bit abstract to be fair but
hypothetically distributed tracing is
creating a schema out of basically
Network annotations somebody will yell
at me for just simplifying it to that I
would tell them that's what it is but
same goal in mind if you know what the
data is you can take action on it it's
not quite entirely true because tracing
is much more free form for example it
doesn't say if you have a SQL statement
it should be like this it should be
formatted this way things like that
whereas like stack traces there's a file
name there's there's a line number
there's like all these things right and
so that's how I think about the Delta
between what it's useful information
what isn't I guess and what allows you
to actually build things like Sentry
versus just build abstract exploration
tools
so
kind of paint the picture of how someone
would get started with a tool like
Sentry do they need to tell Sentry
anything about their application do they
need to modify their source code at all
give us a picture of how that works
yeah like one of our fundamentals which
I think applies for any real business
these days is you've got to like reduce
user friction right like you've got to
make it dead simple to use and for us
there was like kind of a fundamental
driving constraint behind that so in
many situations APM vendors especially
will require you to run an agent
basically like some kind of process that
runs on your servers somewhere well if
you look at modern tech Stacks that
doesn't really work because I don't run
the servers half my stuff's in the
browser or to mobile app or a desktop
app and even if I do have those servers
it's like an entirely different team
that controls them so deploying like a
sidecar an agent is actually like much
more complicated and so we looked at
that and also because like it's much
easier to have control if you just ship
within the application we're like okay
let's build like an SDK a dependency
that just injects into the the
application that runs set an API key and
then you're done and so what that
translates for century is we spent a lot
of time knowing what Django is or what
rails is or what expresses like all
these Frameworks and just knowing how to
plug into the right
Frameworks and then at that point like
the user doesn't have to do anything and
so like the ideal outcome for Sentry is
like you install the dependency in
whatever language makes sense right you
somehow configure the API key and maybe
there's a couple other minor settings
you add and that gives you the Bare
Bones and that's it like it should just
work from there now there's a lot you
can do on top of that to enrich data and
whatnot but for the most part especially
for errors like that's good enough and
that that's always been a fundamental
cooler bars and I think we actually do
it phenomenally well
so it sounds like it infers things about
the application without manual
configuration
can you give some examples of the kind
of things that Sentry knows without the
user having to tell it
yeah so a good example so on the other
side we know literally everything
because an error object in each language
has all these attributes with it it
gives you the sac trace it gives you a
lot of these things so that one's
straightforward on the performance side
we use a combination of leveraging some
like open source I guess implementations
like open Telemetry where it's got all
this instrumentation all ready and we
can just soak that in as well as we
automatically instrument a bunch of
stuff so for example say you've got like
a python application and you're using
let's say like SQL Alchemy or something
I don't actually know if this is how our
SDK works right now but we will build
something that's aware of that library
and make sure it can automatically
instrument the things it needs to get
the right information out of it and be
fair that's always been true for like
APM vendors and stuff like that the
Deltas we've often gone a lot deeper and
so for python for example
you plug it into an application we'll
capture things like the error error
object which is like exception class
name exception value right stack Trace
file name line number all those normal
things function name we'll also collect
source code so we'll give you sort of
surrounding source code blocks for each
line in the stack Trace which makes it
infinitely easier to consume and then in
Python and PHP and I forget if we do
this anywhere else right now we'll
actually even allow you to collect what
are called stack locals so it'll it'll
give you basically the variables that
are defined almost like a debugger and
that is actually actually like game
changing from a development point of
view because if I can go look in
production when there's an incident or a
bug and I can actually see the state of
the application I never need to know
like oh what was going on here oh what
if like do I need to go reproduce this
somehow I always have the right
information
and so all of that for us is automatic
and we only succeed like it's by
definition inside of Sentry it has to be
automatic like if we ask the user to do
anything whatsoever we're failing and so
whenever we design any product or
anything to be fair this is how every
Product Company should operate it's got
to be with as little user input as
humanly possible and so you can't always
pull that off sometimes you have to have
users configure stuff but the goal
should always be no input so you're
talking about getting a stacked Trace
getting the stated variables source code
that sounds like that's primarily going
to be through unhandled exceptions would
you say that's the primary way that you
get errors yeah you can integrate in
other ways so you can like trigger our
API to capture an exception you can also
for better or worse it's not always good
you can integrate through login adapters
so if you're already using a login
framework and you log their errors there
we can often capture those however I
will say in most cases people use the
login apis wrong and the data becomes
junk a good example of this is like it
varies per language so I'm just going to
go to python because python is like sort
of quarter Century in Python you have
the ability to log messages you can log
them as errors you can log like actual
error objects as errors but what usually
happens is somebody does a try catch
they they capture the air they rescue
from it
they create a login call like log dot
error or something put the error message
or value in there and then they send it
upstream and what happens is the stack
Trace is gone because we don't know that
it's an error object and so for example
in Python there's actually a flag you
pass the login call to make sure that
stack tray stays present but if you
don't know that the data becomes junk
all of a sudden and if we don't have a
stack Trace we can't actually aggregate
data because like there's just not
enough information like to run hashing
on it so there are a lot of ways I guess
to capture the information but there are
like good ways and there are bad ways
and I think
it's in everybody's benefit when they
design their their app to like build
some of these abstractions and so like
as an example whenever I would start a
new project these days I will add some
kind of helper function for me to like
log an exception when I like try catch
and then I can just plug in whatever I
need later if I want to enrich the data
or if I want to send that to Century
manually or send it to logs manually it
just makes life a lot easier versus
having to go back and like augment every
single call in the code base you know so
it sounds like when you're using a tool
like Sentry there's going to be the the
unhandled exceptions which are ones that
you weren't expecting so those should I
guess happen without you catching them
and then the ones that you perhaps do
anticipate but you still consider to be
a problem you would catch that and then
you would add some kind of logging
statement to your code that talks to
Sentry directly potentially yeah it
becomes a personal choice to be fair at
that point one of the ways we've been
thinking about this lately because we've
been changing our error monitoring
product to not just be about errors so
we call it issues and that's in the guys
that like it's like an issue tracker a
bug tracker we started putting what are
effectively like
almost like static analysis concerns
inside of this issue tracker so for
example in our performance monitor we'll
do something called like detect n plus
one queries which is where you execute a
duplicate query in a loop it's not
necessarily an error it might not be
causing a problem but it couldn't be
causing a problem in the future
but it's like you know the qualities of
it are not the same as an error like
it's not necessarily causing the user to
experience above and so we've started
thinking more about this and and this is
the same as like logging errors that you
handle it's like well they're not really
air they're not really bugs it's like
expected Behavior but maybe you still
want to keep it like tracking so when I
think about like you know linters and
things like that where it's like well
I've got some things that I definitely
should be fixing then I've got a bunch
of other stuff that's like informing me
that maybe I should take action on or
not but only I the human can really know
at the end of the day right if I if I
should prioritize that or not and so
that's how I kind of think about like if
I'm gonna try catch and then log is like
yeah you should probably collect that
data it's probably less important than
like these other concerns like like an
actual unhandled exception but you do
want to know that they're happening and
whatnot and so
better Century has not had a strong
opinion on this historically we're just
like send us whatever you want to
capture in this regard and you can pay
for it that's fine it's like usage based
you know but we're starting to think a
lot more about what should that look
like if we if we go back to like what's
the what's the opinion we have for how
you should use the product or how you
should solve these kinds of software
problems so you gave the example of
detecting n plus one queries is that
like being aware of the framework or the
orm the person is using and that's how
you're determining this or is it at more
of a lower level than that it is yeah
it's at the framework level so this is
actually where open Telemetry causes a
lot of harm for us because we need to
know what a database query is we need to
know like the structure of the query
because we actually want to parse it out
in a lot of cases because we actually
need to identify if it's duplicate right
and we need to know that it's a database
query not a random annotation that
you've added and so what we do is Within
These traces which is like if you if you
don't know what a trace is it's
basically just like
it's a tree like a tree structure so
it's like a calls B calls c b also calls
d and e and Etc right and so you just
you know it's a trace and so we actually
just look at that Trace data we try to
find these patterns which is like okay B
was a a SQL query or something and every
single sibling of B is that same SQL
query but sort of removing certain
parameters and stuff for the value so
we'll look at that data and we'll try to
pull out anomaly so n plus one is an
example of like a fairly obvious
anti-pattern that everybody knows is bad
and can be optimized but there's a lot
of other that are a little bit more
subjective I'll give you an example if
you execute three SQL statements back to
back one could argue that you could just
batch those SQL statements together I
would argue most of the time it doesn't
matter and I don't need to do that and
also it's not guaranteed that that is
better so it becomes much more like well
in my particular situation this is
valuable but in this other situation it
might not be and that's where I go back
to like it's almost like a linter you
know but we're trying to infer all of
that from the data stream so so
centuries kind of we're kind of a
backwards Product Company so we build
our product from a technology Vision not
from customers want this or we have this
great product Vision or anything like
that and so in our case the technology
vision is like there's a lot of
application data that comes in a lot of
telemetry right errors traces we have a
bunch of other streams now within that
Telemetry there is like signal and so
one it's all structured data so we know
what it is we can actually interpret it
and then we can identify that signal
that might be a problem and that signal
in our case is often going to translate
to like this issue concept and then the
goal is like well can we identify these
problems for people and surface them
versus the Choose Your Own Adventure
model which is like we'll just capture
everything and feed it to the user and
they can figure out what matters because
again a web service is a web service the
database is a database they're all the
same problems for everybody all you know
it's just and so that's kind of the
model we built in our continuing to
evolve on and so far works pretty well
to curate a lot of these workflows see
you talked a little bit about how people
will sometimes use tracing and in cases
like that they may need some kind of
session ID to track
somebody making a call to a service and
that talks to a database and that talks
to other services and inside of your
application you have to
instrument some way of tracking this all
came from this one request is that
something that Sentry can infer or is
there something that the developer has
to put into play so that you can track
that sort of thing yeah so it's like a
bit of both and I would say our goal is
that we can infer everything the reality
is there is so much complexity and
there's too much of it like too many
Technologies in the world like I was
complaining about this the other day
like a classic example in web services
if we have a middleware hook we kind of
know request response usually that's how
middleware would work right and so we
can infer a lot from there like
basically we can infer the boundaries
which is a really big deal okay that's
one thing is boundaries is a problem
what we we describe that as a
transaction so like when the request
starts when the request ends right
that's a very important boundary for
everybody to understand because when I'm
working on the API I care about the API
boundary I actually don't care about
what the database is doing at its low
level or what the JavaScript application
might be doing above it I want my
boundary so that's one that we kind of
can do but it's hard in a lot of
situations because of the way Frameworks
and technology has been designed but at
least traditional stuff like a
traditional web stack it works like a
rails app or a Django app or a PHP app
kind of thing right and then within that
it becomes well how do you actually
build a trace versus just have a bunch
of arbitrary labels and so we have a
bunch of complicated Tech within each
language that tries to establish that
tree and then we annotate a lot of
things along the way and so we will
either leverage open Telemetry which is
an open format spec that ideally has
very high quality data ideally not
realistically but ideally it has high
quality data every Library author
implements it great everybody's happy we
don't have to do anything ever again the
reality is that data is like all over
the map because there's not like strict
requirements for what how the data
should be labeled and stuff and not
everything even has that data like not
everything's instrumented with open
Telemetry so we also have a bunch of
stuff that unrelated to using that will
say okay we know what this library is
we're going to try to infer some
characteristics from this library or we
know what maybe like the Django template
engine is so we're going to try to infer
like when the template renders so you
can capture that block of information it
is a very imperfect science and I would
tell you like it's not
even though like open Telemetry is a
very fun topic for people it is not
necessarily good like it's not in a good
State could will it ever be good I don't
know in all honesty but like the data
quality is like all over the map and so
that's honestly one of our biggest
challenges to making this experience
that you know tells you what's going on
in your database so it tells you what's
going on with the cash or things like
this is like
I know the cash might be called
something completely random in one
implementation and something totally
different in another and so it's a lot
of like like data normalization that you
have to deal with but for the most part
those libraries have since you don't
control Canon will be instrumented now
the other interesting thing which we'll
see how this works out so one thing
Sentry tries to do there we have all
these layers of telemetry so we have
errors and traces right those are pretty
high level Concepts we also have
profiling data which is very very very
very very low level so it's usually only
if you have like this guy like
it's where is all the CPU time being
spent in my application mostly not
waiting like waiting is usually like a
network call right but it's like okay I
have a loop that's doing a lot of math
or I'm writing a bunch of stuff to disk
and that's really slow like often those
are not instrumented or it's like these
black box areas of a performance and so
what we're trying to do with profiling
data instead of just showing you flame
charts and stuff is actually say could
we fill in these gaps in these traces
like basically like hey I've got a long
period of time where the app's doing
something you know here's an API call
here's the database stuff but then
there's this block okay what's that
function or something can we pull that
out of the profiling data and so in that
case again that's just automatic because
the profile actually knows everything
about the application and no it has full
access to the function and the stack and
everything right and so the dream is
that
you would just always have everything
filled in the customer never has to do
anything with one minor asterisk and the
asterisk is what I would call like
business context so a good example would
be
you might want to associate requests
with a specific customer or something
like that like you might want to say
well it's I don't know Goldman Sachs or
one of these big companies or something
so you can know like well when Goldman
Sachs is having performance issues or
whatever it is oh maybe I should focus
on them because maybe they pay you a lot
of money or something right since you
would never know that at the end of the
day so we also have these like kind of
tagging contextual apis that will say
like tell us some informations maybe
it's like customer maybe it's something
else that's relevant to your application
and we'll keep that data associated with
the time a tree that's like present you
know but that at least the Telemetry
like again applications just work the
same there should be a day in the next
few years that it's just all automatic
and again the only challenge today is
like can it be high quality and
automatic and so that that's like to be
determined what you're kind of saying is
the ideal is being able to look at this
profiling information and be able to
build a full picture of a call from
beginning to end all the different
things to talk to
but yeah I guess what's their what's the
reality today like what is
Century able to determine in the world
we live in right now
so we've done a lot of this like
performance detection stuff already so
we actually can do a lot now we put a
lot of time into it and I will tell you
if you look at other tools trying to do
tracing their approach is much more
abstract it's like your traditional
monitoring tool that's like we're just
going to collect a lot of signals and
maybe we'll find magic anomaly detection
or something going on in it which you
know props anybody that can figure that
out but
a lot of what we've done is like okay we
kind of know what this data looks like
let's go after this very like known
quantity problem let's normalize the
data and let's make it happen like
that's today the enrichment of profiles
is new for us but it we actually can
already do it it's not perfect and I
think we're launching something in April
or May something around that time frame
where hopefully for the the Technologies
we could instrument we're actually able
to surface that in a useful way but as
an example that that concept that I was
talking about like with n plus one
queries the team built something using
profiling data and I think this this
might be for like a mobile app more so
than anything where mobile apps have
this problem of it's you've got a main
thread and if you block that main thread
the app is basically Frozen you see this
on desktop apps all the time you you
very rarely see it on web apps anymore
but but it's a really big problem when
you have a mobile or desktop app because
you don't want that like thing to be
non-responsive right and so one of the
things they did was detect when you're
doing like file i o on the main thread
you know right when you're writing a
disk which is power probably a slow
thing or something like that that's
going to block the whole thing because
you should just do it on a separate
thread it's like an easy fix potentially
may not be a problem but it could become
a problem same thing as n plus one but
what's really interesting about it is
what the team did is like they used the
profiling data to detect it because we
already know threads and everything in
there and then they actually recreated a
stack Trace out of that profiling data
when it's surfaced so it's actually like
useful data that you could like that I
or you as a developer might know how to
take and actually like oh this is where
it happens in the source code I can
actually figure it out and go fix it
myself enemy like as like I'm still very
much in the weeds with software that is
like one of the biggest gaps to most
things is it just it doesn't make it
easy to consume or like take action on
right like if I've got a chart that says
my error rate is high what am I going to
do with that I'm like okay what's
breaking that's immediately my next
question right okay this is the error
where is that error happening at again
my next question it's literally just
root cause analysis right and so that to
me is very exciting I don't know that
we're the first people to do that I'm
not sure but like if we can make that
kind of data that level of actionable
and consumable that's like a big deal
for me because I will tell you is like I
have 20 years of software experience
I still hate flame charts and like I
struggle to use them like they're not a
friendly visualization they're almost
like a hypothetically necessary evil but
I also think one where nobody said like
do we even need to use that do we need
that to be like the way we operate
anyways like I guess that's my
long-winded way of saying like I'm very
excited for how we can leverage that
data and change how it's used yeah so it
sounds like in this example both in the
mobile app blocking the UI or the N plus
one query is
the century I suppose SDK
instrumentation that's hooked inside of
your application there are certain
behaviors that it knows are are not like
ideal I guess just based on people's
prior experience like your own
developers know that hey if you block
the UI thread in this mobile application
then you're gonna have performance
problems and so that way rather than
just telling you hey your app is slow it
can tell you your app is slow and it's
because you're blocking the UI thread
exactly and I actually think
I don't know why so many people don't
recognize this Gap because at the end of
the day like I don't need more people to
tell me response times are bad or
anything I need you to have an opinion
about what's good because the only way
it's like math education right like yeah
you learn the basics but you're not
expected to say go to calc but and then
like do all the fundamentals you're like
don't get a calculator and start
simplifying the problem like yeah we're
gonna teach you a few of these things so
you understand it we're gonna teach you
how to use a calculator and then just
use the calculator and then make it
easier for everybody else but we're also
not teaching you how to build a
calculator because who cares like that's
not the purpose of it and so for me this
is like
we should be helping people sort of get
to the Finish Line instead of making
them run the entirety of the race over
and over if they don't need to I don't
know if that's a good analogy but but
that has been the biggest Gap I think in
so much of this software throughout the
industry and it's common everywhere
and there's no reason for that Gap to
exist these days like the technology
spine the technology has been fine for
like 10 years like Century started in 08
at this point and I think there was only
one other company I recall at the time
that was doing anything that was even
similar to like air monitoring and
essentially when we built it we're just
like what if we just go deeper what if
we collect all this information that
will help you debug the problem instead
of just stopping it like a log
aggregator or something kind of thing so
we can actually have an opinion about it
and I genuinely it baffles me that more
people do not think this way because it
was not a hard problem at the time it's
certainly not hard these days I mean a
lot more people do it now they've seen
Century successful and there's a lot of
similar implementations but it just
amazes me it's like why don't you why
don't people try to make the data more
actionable and more useful to teams
versus just collect more of it you know
and so I guess based on this it sounds
like
maybe the popularity of the stack the
person is using or of the framework
means that you're going to have better
insights right like if somebody makes a
a Django application or a rails
application there's all these lessons
that your team has picked up in terms of
hey if you use the orm this way your
application is going to be slow whereas
if somebody
build something totally homegrown you
won't know these patterns and you won't
be able to like help as much basically
yeah yeah that's exactly and you might
think that that is a challenge but then
you look at how many employees exist at
like large tech companies and it's it's
not that big of a deal like you might
even think collecting all the
information for each like programming
runtime or framework is a challenge we
have like 40 people that work on that
and it's totally fine like and so I
think actually all these scale just fine
but you do have to understand like the
domain right and so the counter version
of this is if you look at say like
browser applications like very rich
single page application type experiences
it's not really obvious like what the
opinions are like if you and this is
like really like if you go to Century
it's it's kind of slow like the app is
kind of slow we even make fun of
ourselves for how slow it is because
it's a lot of JavaScript and stuff if
you ask somebody internally hey how
would we make pick a page fast
they're gonna have no clue like even if
they have like infinite domain
experience they're gonna be like I'm not
entirely sure because there's a lot of
like moving parts and it's not even
clear what like like good is right like
we know n plus one is bad so we can say
not doing that is the better solution
and so if you have a Javascript app
which is like where a lot of the
slowness will come from is like the
render times itself like how do you fix
it you can't actually build a product
that tells you what to fix without
knowing how to fix it right and so some
of these newer and very fast moving
targets are are frankly very difficult
for us and so that's one thing that I
think is a challenge for the entire
industry and so like as an example a lot
of the browser folks have latched onto
web vitals which are just metrics that
hopefully tell you something about the
application but they're not always
actionable either it'll be like the idea
with like web vitals is like okay time
to interactive is an important metric
it's like how long until the page loads
that a user can do what they're probably
there to do okay
abstractly it makes sense to us but like
put into action
how do I optimize time to interactive
don't block the page that's one thing I
don't know defer assets that's another
thing okay so you've gotta like you've
got to build a technology that knows
these assets could be deferred and
aren't okay which ones can be deferred I
don't know like it's like such a deep
rabbit hole and then the problem is six
months from now the tech will have
completely changed right and it won't
have like necessarily solved some of
these problems it will just have changed
and they're now a completely different
shape of problem but still the same
fundamental like user experience is the
same you know and to me that's like the
biggest challenge in the industry right
now is that like dilemma of the browser
at the end of the day and so even from
our end we're like okay maybe we should
step back focus on servers again focus
on web services those are known
quantities we can do that really well we
can sort of change that to be better
than it's been in the past and easier to
consume with things like our n plus one
detections and then take like a holistic
fresh look at browser and say okay now
how would we solve this to make sure we
could actually really latch down to the
problems that like people have and and
we understand right and you know we'll
see when we get there I don't think any
product does a great job these days for
helping solve those problems
but I think even without the the
products like I said like even our team
would be like fixing this is going to
take months because it's going to take
months just to figure out exactly where
the the common bottlenecks are and all
these other things within an application
and so I guess what I mean to say with
that is there's a lot of opportunity I
think with the moving landscape of
Technology if we can find a way to
whether it's standardized or Sentry can
find a way to make that data actionable
want something in between there so it
sounds like what you're saying is with
the back end there's almost like a
standard way of doing things or a way
that a lot of people do it the same way
whereas on the front end even if you're
looking at a react application you could
look at tenant react applications and
they could all be doing State Management
a totally different way they could be
like the way that the application is
structured could be totally different
and that makes it difficult for you to
infer sort of these
standard patterns on the front end side
yeah that's definitely true and it goes
it's even worse than that because the
applications often well one there's just
like the nature of JavaScript which is
asynchronous in the sense of like it's a
lot of callbacks and things like that
and so that already makes it hard to
understand what's going on where things
are happening and then you have these
abstractions like react which are very
good but like they pull a lot of that
away and so as an example of a common
problem you load the application it has
to do a lot of stuff to make the page
render you might call that hydration or
whatever okay and then there's a
completely different state which is
going from it's already hydrated page
one I've done an interaction or
something or maybe I've navigated a page
two that's an entirely different like
sort of performance problem but that
hydration time that's like a known thing
that's kind of like time to interactive
right but if the problem is in your
framework which a lot of it is like a
lot of the problems today exist because
of Frameworks not because the technology
is bad or the framework's bad but just
because it's abstracted and it's really
hard to make it work in all these
situations it's complicated and again
they have the same problem where it's
like changing Non-Stop and so if the
problem is the framework is somehow
incorrectly re-rendering the page as an
example and this came up recently for
some big technology stack it's
re-rendering the page that's a really
bad problem for the customer because
it's making that it's probably actually
causing a lot of CPU seconds that's why
like your Chrome browser Tabs are using
so much memory and CPU right
how do you fix that can you even fix
that do you just say I don't know blame
the technology is that the solution
maybe that is right but how would we
even blame the technology like that
alone just to identify why it's
happening and you need to know the why
right like that is such a hard problem
these days and personally I think the
only solution is if the industry sort of
almost like standardized is on a way to
like on a belief of how this should be
optimized and how it should be measured
and monitored kind of thing because like
how errors work is like a
standardization effectively it may not
be like a formal like Declaration of
like this is what an error is but more
or less they always have the same
attributes because we've all kind of
understood that like those are the
valuable things right okay I've got a
server rendered application that has
client interaction which is sort of the
current generation of the technology we
need to standardize on what like that
web request like response life cycle is
right and what are the moving targets
within there and it's just to me I
honestly feel like a lot of what we use
every day and technology is like beta
software
and I think it's one of the reasons why
we're constantly always having a like
upgrade and and refactor and and shift
dependencies and things like that
because it is not it's very much a
prototype right it's a moving Target
which I personally do not think is great
for the industry because like customers
do not care they do not care that you're
using some technology that like needs to
change every few months and things like
that now it has improved things to be
fair like web applications are much more
like interactive and responsive
sometimes but it is a very hard problem
I think for a lot of people in the world
and when you refer to things feeling
like
beta I suppose are you referring to the
Frameworks people are using or the
libraries they're using to support their
front-end development I'm curious what
you're thinking there I think it's
everything
like the browser apis are constantly
shifting that's gotten a little bit
better but even the idea like typescript
and stuff it's like we're running
basically compilers to make all this
code work and so that even that they're
constantly adding features just because
they can which means the behaviors are
constantly changing but like if you look
at a real world example like react is
like the most dominant technology it's
very well designed for managing the Dom
it's basically just a rendering engine
at the end of the day it's like it's
managed to process updates to the Dom
okay makes sense but we've all learned
that these massive single page
applications where you build all your
application logic and loaded into a
bundle is a problem like I don't know
how big sentries bundle is but it's
multiple Megs in size and it takes a
little while for like even on Fast fiber
here in the Bay Area it takes you know
several seconds for the UI to load and
that's not ideal like at some point half
of us became okay with this
so we're like okay what we need to do is
go back literally just go back 10 years
and we need to render it on the server
and then we need some stuff that makes
interactions you know highly responsive
in the UI or dynamic content in the UI
you know it's like bringing back jQuery
or something and so we're kind of going
full circle but that is actually like
very complicated because the way people
are trying to do is like okay we wanna
we wanna have the rendering engine
operate the same on the server as on the
client right so it's like we just write
one pack of code that basically it's
like a template engine to some degree
right and okay that makes sense like we
can all get behind that kind of model
but that is actually really hard to make
work with a lot of people's software and
I think the challenge and framers have
adopted it right so they've taken this
so for example it's like react server
components which is basically just like
can we render it on the server and then
also keep that same interaction in the
UI but the problem is like framers take
that they abstract it and so it's
another layer of complexity on something
that is already enormously complex and
then they add their own flavor on it
like their own opinions for maybe what
the way the world is going and I will
say like personally I find those flavors
to be very hard to adapt to like things
that are tried and true or importantly
in this context things that we know how
to monitor and fix right and so I don't
know what to be all I know is but my
thesis on this is you need to treat the
UI like a template engine and that's it
remove all like complexity behind it and
so if you think about that the term I've
labeled it as which I did not come up
with I saw this from somebody at some
point it's like you're front end as a
service like you need to take that
application that renders on the server
in the front end and it's just an
entirely different application which is
annoying and it just calls your apis and
that's how it gets the data it needs so
you're literally just treating it as if
it's like a single page application
that can't connect to your database but
the Frameworks have not quite done that
and they're like no no we'll connect to
the database and we'll do all this stuff
but then it doesn't work because you've
got like it works this way on the back
end and this way on the front end
anyways again long-winded way of saying
like it's very complicated I don't think
the technology can solve it today I
think the technology has to change
before these problems can actually
genuinely become solvable and that's why
I think the whole thing is like a beta
it's very much like a moving Target that
eventually will get there and it's
definitely had value but I don't know
that responsiveness for low latency
connections is where the value has been
created you know for like folks with bad
internet and say remote Africa or
something like I'm sure the internet is
not a very fun place for them to use
these days I guess one of the things you
mentioned is there's this almost like
the split where you have the application
running on the server it has its own set
of rules because it like you said has
access to the database and it can do
things that you can't do in the browser
and then you have to sort of run the
same application in the browser but it's
not quite the same application in
because it doesn't have access to the
same things in the browser so you have
this weird
disconnect I suppose yeah and and then
the challenges is like a developer
that's actually complicated for you from
the experience point of view because you
have to know somehow okay these things
these are actually running on the server
and only on the server and like so I
think the two biggest technologies that
try to do this or at least do it well
enough or the to that I've used there
might be some others are nexjs and remix
and they have very different takes on
how to do this but remix is the one I
used most recently so I'll comment on
that but like there's a way that you
kind of say well this only runs on I
think the client as an example and that
helps you a little bit you're like okay
this is only going to render on the
client I actually can think about that
and reason about that but then there's
this thing like okay sometimes this runs
on the server only this part runs on the
server and it just becomes like the
mental capacity to figure out what's
going on and debug it is like so
difficult and that database problem is
like the normal problem right like of
like I can only query the database on
the server because I need secure
credentials or something okay I
understand that as a develop but I don't
understand how to make sure the
application is doing what I expect to do
and how to fix it if something goes
wrong and that's why I think I'm a
Believer in constraints the only way you
make progress is you simplify problems
like you just give up on solving the
complicated thing and you make the
problem simpler right and so for me
that's why I'm like just take the
database out of the equation we can
create apis from the client from the
server same security levels okay make it
so it can only do that and it has to be
run as almost like a UI only thing now
that creates complexity because you have
to run this other service right and and
like I personally do not want to have to
spin up a bunch of containers just to
write like a simple like web application
but again I think the problem has not
been simplified yet for a lot of folks
like reacted this to be fair it made it
a lot easier to build UI that was
responsive and just updated values when
they changed you know which was a big
deal for a long period of time but I
feel like everything after has not quite
reached that area was it simple and even
react is hard to debug whether it
doesn't do what you wanted to do so I
don't know there's still gaps I guess is
what I would say and hopefully hopefully
you know in the next five years we'll
kind of see this come to completion
because it does feel like
it's getting closer to that compromise
you know where like we used to have pure
server rendered apps with some weird
janky JavaScript on top now we've got
this bridge of really complicated
JavaScript on top and the server apps
are also complicated and it's a
nightmare and then this newer generation
of these Frameworks that work for some
types of Technology but not all and
we're kind of almost coming full circle
to like server rendered you know
everything but with like allowing the
same level of interactions that we've
been Desiring I guess on the web so
fingers crossed this gets better but
right now I do not see like a clear like
oh it's definitely there I can see it
coming I'm like when we're kind of
making progress I don't love being the
beta tester of the whole thing but we're
kind of getting there and so you know
we'll see I guess you you've been saying
this whole shifting landscape of how
front end Works has made it difficult
for Century to provide like automatic
instrumentation and things like that for
mobile apps is that a different story
like is it pretty standardized in terms
of how do you instrument an Android app
or an IOS app
sort of but also no like a good example
here is like early days mobile it's a
native application you ship a binary
known quantity right or maybe you embed
in a web browser but like that was like
a very different thing okay and then
they did things were like okay more of
it's like embedded web browser type
stuff or dynamically rendered content so
that's now a moving Target the current
version of that which I'm not a mobile
Dev so like people have strong opinions
on both sides of this fence but it's
like okay do you use like a hybrid
framework which allows you to build say
react native which is like Rousy or
sorta right a javascript-ish thing and
it runs on both Android and mobile but
not really well on either or do you
write a native app which is like a known
quantity but then you maintain like two
code bases have two degrees of expertise
and stuff flutters the same thing so
there's still that version of complexity
that goes on within it and I I think
people care less about mobile because it
impacts people less like there's that
whole generation of like oh Mobile's the
future everything's gonna be mobile
that's not become true mobile is very
important but like we have desktop still
we use web software all the time half
the time a mobile we're just using the
web software of the day so at least we
know that's a thing so I think that
investment in Mobile has died down some
but some companies like mobile is like
their main experience or one of their
driving experiences like a company like
doordash mobile is as important as web
if not more right because of like the
types of customers Spotify probably same
thing but I don't know Century we don't
need a mobile app who cares it's
irrelevant to the problem space right
and so
I think it's just not quite taken on and
so mobile is still like this secondary
citizen that a lot of companies and I
think the evolution of it has been like
complicated and so I I think a lot of
the problems are known
but maybe people care less or they're
just less customers and so the weight
doesn't like the weight is wildly
different like javascript's probably
like 100 times the size from an
investment point of view for everyone in
the world than same mobile applications
are is how I would think about it and so
whether mobile is or isn't solved is
almost irrelevant to the general problem
at hand and I think at the very least
like mobile application there's like a
tool chain where you can debug a lot of
stuff that works fairly well it hasn't
changed over the years whereas like the
web you have like browser tools but
that's about it so
yeah so I guess with mobile I was
initially thinking of native apps but
you're bringing up that there's actually
people who would make a native app
that's just a web view for a web page or
there's react native or there's flutter
so there's actually it really isn't
standard how to make a mobile app yeah
and even within those it comes back to
like okay is it now the same problem
where we're loading in a bunch of
JavaScript or downloading a bunch of
JavaScript and content remotely and
stuff and like you'll see this when you
install a mobile app and sometimes the
binaries are huge right sometimes
they're really small and then you load
it up and it's downloading like several
gigs of data and stuff right and those
are completely different patterns and
even within those like subsets I'm sure
the implementations are wildly different
right and so that may not be the same as
like the runtime kind of changing but I
remember there was this this must be a
decade ago I still am a gamer but early
in my career I worked a lot with like
Games like World of Warcraft and stuff
and I remember when games started
launching Progressive loading where it's
like you could download a small chunk of
the game and actually start playing and
maybe the textures were lower like
resolution and everything was low
Fidelity and and you could only go so
far until the game fully installed but
imagine like if you're like focused on
performance or something like that
measuring it there is completely
different than measuring it one say
everything's installed you know and so I
think those often become very complex
use cases and I think that used to be
like an extreme Edge case that was like
such a a hyper-specific optimization for
like World of Warcraft which is like one
of the biggest games of all time that it
made sense you know okay whatever they
can build their own custom tooling and
figure it out from there and now we've
taken that degree of complexity and
trying to apply to everything in the
world and it's like oh like nobody has
the teams or the talent or the
experience to necessarily debug a lot of
these complicated problems just like
Century like you know we're not dealing
with react internals if something's
wrong in the react internals it's like
somebody might be able to figure it out
but it's going to take us so much time
to figure out what's going on versus oh
we're rendering some HTML cool we
understand how it works it's a No-No
problem we can debug it like there's
nothing to even debug most of the time
right and so I don't know I think the
industry has to get to a place where you
can reason about the software where you
have the calculator right and you don't
have to figure out how the calculator
works you just can trust it it's going
to work for you so kind of Shifting over
a little bit to centuries and internals
you said that Century started in was it
2008 you said the open source project
was in 2008 yeah the stack that's used
in Century has evolved like I remember
that there was a period where I think
you could run it with a pretty minimal
stack like I think I may have even
supported SQL Lite yeah and so it was
something that people could run pretty
easily on their own but things have
obviously changed a lot and so I wonder
if you could speak to sort of the
evolution of that process like when do
you decide like hey this thing that I
built in 2008 is not going to cut it and
I really need to re-architect what the
system is
yeah so I don't know if that's actually
the reality of why things have changed
that it's like oh this doesn't work
anymore we've definitely introduced
complexity in the sense of like
probably the biggest shift for a century
was like it used to be everything was a
SQL database and everything was kind of
optional
I think half of that was maintainable
because it was mostly built by me and so
I could maintain like an architectural
Vision that kept it minimal I had
experience to figure it out and duct
tape the right things
so that was one thing and I think
eventually you know that doesn't scale
as you're trying to do more and build
more into the product so there's some
complexity there but for the most part
it can still be a SQL database whatever
could it be SQL light forever probably
not but it was gold when you could run
SQL light in the development environment
because it was super fast right and so
then there was like the evolution of
that to where we started adding more
complex services so one example was we
needed a key value store and we needed
like store blob data because story of
them in the SQL database was highly
inefficient in becoming very expensive
and so we wrote just an abstraction that
could sort in the database or in the
technology at the time was react r-i-a-k
not to be confused with react and that
was just like you can almost think of it
like uh bigtable or naively S3 or
something it's literally just like get
set delete where the operation is
available to us and that actually worked
totally fine so it meant like we could
swap it out for more scalable technology
but you could also ignore swapping it
out and at some point you've got like a
maintenance burden for like handling
these different code paths right because
that's also the era when century was
only open source or primarily open
source so primarily just ran it yourself
you know then we started adopting SAS
we're starting to build more complexity
basically the constraints we put into
place are actually causing problems now
so we need to change the constraints
which means supporting all these things
it's hard so that's one thing that
happens right now I would not excuse it
and say you couldn't still keep things
simple I think that's a thing but that
takes a lot of rigor and at some point
you're like is it worth it you know
especially when primarily especially in
this day and age things are just SAS
services and we've all kind of accepted
that but that was one and then there was
a big shift where we wanted to consume
and make scalable and fast a lot of data
right like there's already lots of
Errors I don't know how many like I'm
certain Sentry like sucks in hundreds of
thousands of events a second on a bad
day on a slow day so I'm sure it's a
huge amount of data that we get these
days and that takes a certain scale
right and it's actually very hard to
handle small scale and large scale at
some point and obviously we're
optimizing for the SAS so at some point
we're like okay let's we need a better
solution for storing the events
something that we'll be able to like
write them in search them very fast take
a lot of the load off the database and
so we adopt a clickhouse and I think
that's kind of when that's like the
whatever the saying is like straw that
broke the camel's back or something I
don't know the same but where everything
started to get more complex and that's
when all of a sudden it's like you need
15 Docker containers and this isn't even
micro services this isn't even like the
worst version of this hell you know it's
just like and I think it's unfortunate
that that's like what it's come to is
like you have to run a lot of these
complex services
and I think this is not even
representative of just centuries growth
it's like the whole industry where we've
we've made things a little bit more
complicated than it needs to be in a lot
of cases and so I think it's just like
it was that shift and then that's like
when we wanted to build performance
monitoring we needed all these new
things and even in the product today
like if you just want to use it for
error monitoring whether you're a SAS
customer or self-hosted there's still a
lot going on right okay maybe that's
fine maybe that's a reality but right
now like this year we're going to redo a
lot of the product because it's too
complicated there's too much going on
and it becomes like a distraction like
you load up the AWS console or even gcp
is just as bad these days where there's
like 800 different services and you're
like who cares like why do I need any of
this and half of them are the same thing
and that is the worst part is half of
them are the same thing or they're not
achieving different goals would be how I
think about it and Sentry is not that
but the biggest companies in our space
are that like if you use datadog it's
the same thing there's like go to the
datadog's pricing page and you're like
oh my god there are so many different
things in here I don't even know what
the difference is between some of these
products right and so we're very
conscious of this and I think I don't
know that we can reduce the technology
complexity that much if at all these
days other than maybe make it a little
bit easier to not have to run everything
for the open source side of things but
the product burden is still there when
you're like how do I even reason about
all this stuff that's going on and why
does it even need to happen this way so
I don't know it's like a sad thing to
some degree but at the same time like
we've been able to build like such a
significant product that works for so
many different people and it solves so
many different problems and it's still
you can not as easily but you can still
can run it on your own hardware and I'm
amazed when like a single human runs it
on like a VPS or something which it for
newer generation people is a virtual
private server AKA like a linued or a
digital ocean something cheap because it
is a lot of stuff it's a lot of services
to run and a lot of them are Java and
they take a lot of memory so what it
sounds like is that version of the
software that used to be able to run
with pretty minimal dependencies I think
you you know you would have a relational
database I think you had redis in there
and now there's like you said click
house there's zookeeper there's is there
Kafka there is Kafka yeah there's a lot
of different pieces and from what you're
telling me is it's kind of a function of
going from this company that's like
here's this open source software that
anybody can run themselves to this is
really a SAS company this is like we
need to focus on being able to run this
at scale and the use case of somebody
running it themselves or at their own
business is just like kind of not that
important anymore at least to you know
that's not the priority and that's why
you kind of made these decisions because
they were suited to building a SAS
platform that can service a lot of
customers yeah that is a huge chunk of
it I think there was also the thing like
for example that key value store at some
point we supported Cassandra we never
use Cassandra herself but it was in the
code base we're not going to maintain
that it might be broken for all we know
yeah there's a CI system and at some
point you've got to say like no that's
not happening and that was actually a
good decision like less variability is
huge for infrastructure right and that
doesn't require it to be more
complicated but like if we just say too
bad you can't run Cassandra run I don't
know you know big table or something
that we actually use ourselves it's like
maybe you don't want to but it's like
we're not making any money and nobody's
maintaining all these like adapters for
these different databases like we
supported a Django does because so we
sort of did but like Ms SQL which I
assume is still a thing I'm not sure no
idea if it ever worked correctly was
performant or not you know that and
that's the same dilemma sqlite right and
so I think SQL live is fine for
development environments who cares for
production no chance does it function
for us but I don't know so I think it's
sort of a necessary evil but but it
doesn't have to be complicated so a good
example today is we still require
something like rabbitmq and kafta why do
we need two things that are effectively
Brokers we don't it's just like why
would it be a priority to replace like
the old system that powers all this or
combine it with the new system that
powers these new things it's like it's a
lot of engineering work right and so
there is that compromise of velocity in
there that we're forever facing and this
doesn't even begin to touch on like the
newer stuff that we're gonna open source
like I don't even think we've open
source our first acquisition which was
the profiling stuff I think that might
still be closed Source we're going to
open source that we acquired code
recently we're gonna open source that
and so those are more moving parts that
even add more complexity to the product
and so one of the enemy fair this
complexity Cascades in the development
environment and experience and stuff so
it's worthwhile to fix but as an example
you should be able to say I'm just
working on maybe the error stuff or the
issues product so I don't need to run
all this other stuff and that same
decision can also say oh the customer
only wants to like use this for the
heiress product so they don't need to
run all this other stuff right you like
you can solve both of those goals and I
think it just requires intent behind it
doesn't necessarily mean it will make it
that much simpler but it is a path
towards enabling that Simplicity it's
also probably aligning with how the
business is structured right like I
don't think you offer a
self-hosted commercially supported plan
right so
in that regard there isn't really the
need from the company side to say like
hey let's make these cases where you can
deploy it and only install two of the
dependencies because you only need that
much it's like very different from a
system or product that was not really a
SAS or it could be a SAS but also had a
on-premise option like you could take I
suppose atlassian's Suite as an example
where they have their cloud service but
there's also a lot of businesses that
run it on site so there's probably
different decisions that they have to
make yeah 100 and I actually care it's
like you know the model from a
technology angle is probably similar to
gitlab and I I'm not a gitlab user but I
wonder if folks like that have the same
complexity where they're like here's our
15 different products and it's sort of
open sourcy you know and we ours at
least was intentional we're like we're
not building on-prem software we don't
want to be in that business we don't
want these support contracts for
Cassandra and random we basically don't
want to have to have an outsourced Ops
Team you know for this work it's just
not interesting it's not building a
product at the end of the day and so I
think it was like that was probably one
of the best decisions we ever made was
yes it's open source we're building an
Open Source service like a SAS service
at the end of the day and that's the
reality of things right and that was
such a big deal for us because yeah like
it's hard to keep the complexity in
check no matter what if you get to any
reasonable size right and big Ambitions
are one of the most important things you
can have in my opinion for building
anything even if it's not like oh we
want to build a big company you want to
be able to build something that solves
like significant scope of problems right
and there's more value for Century as a
whole cool if we can solve more problems
under sort of the same kind of landscape
right if nothing else because whether
it's true or not the reality is like
nobody wants to run 20 different tools
or whatever it is right like usually
what happens is you have to because like
one tool cannot rule them all but if the
problem is the same shape the technology
should be able to be reused to solve
that problem and that that's where we go
back to like well we have errors and we
have n Plus One issues and they're kind
of the same
so how do we make the product just
surface both of those use cases right
same technology same product for the
most part and then inherently here comes
the complexity so you've mentioned a
little bit about how there are parts of
Sentry that are open source and I know
that there's different licenses applied
to different parts of the product so I
wonder if you could explain sort of how
those decisions are made and maybe you
could explain the business source
license as well yeah so once upon a time
century was BSD licensed and that was
the server itself and Century's got a
lot of Open Source stuff or a lot of
projects and services and stuff but the
core of the server was like super
liberally licensed everything else was
fairly liberally licensed like we never
use gpl's we never use proprietary
licenses we had some closed Source stuff
but it's irrelevant it was like our data
analytics and billing code and stuff
like that but so is all this it was all
just like liberal free you could use it
no strings no open core no nothing right
and then we had constant annoying
conversations with people trying to sell
our software and to be clear Century has
always been built by myself and people
that we've employed at the company
sometimes people contribute small
patches but that's wildly different than
maintaining or actually developing the
software and so it's best to think of
century as like yes it's open source but
it was built by our company the sdks and
Integrations that's different but the
course service right and so we had this
thing where people like companies were
trying to sell it they didn't want to
give back financially or they didn't
contribute both basically and so we're
like this is annoying and this is
literally the decision tree this is
annoying let's stop them from doing that
so we can no longer think about this
problem and so at that point we said
we're going to change How We Do
licensing a Sentry for open source if
it's part of the service the core
service it becomes BSL which I'll
explain in a minute if it's anything
else that doesn't run the course service
like an SDK or anything that needs
embedded in customer applications it
must use a liberal license and so we did
this because I did not want an open core
model an open core if you're not
familiar usually what it translates to
is here's the version of the open source
product that you can use for free no
strings attached and here's the good
version that costs minimum 50 to 100 000
a year or something along those lines it
becomes this obnoxious selling Paradigm
I hate that model so much as a consumer
that I refuse to build it and if it was
not for companies trying to sell our
stuff we would still be BSD or Apache
license for the server right
unfortunately Ximena you can't take on
good faith and definitely in like
capitalism you cannot operate on good
faith so we realized since the BSL and
BSL the way I think about it is
eventually open source and so open
source has a lot of different angles you
can think of it as open sources like
free software that I can use just for
free or open sources like I can take
that software do whatever I want with it
which is the most extreme version or
open source I can use the code in other
ways or something like that right
there's all these kind of variations of
a thing but I think the most are like
I can do whatever I want with it or it's
free and I actually think a lot of
people mostly care about open source
from it's the its free angle and so BSL
What it lets us do is say it's free you
can't sell it so we we blocked off
people from like sort of cannibalizing
our ability to fund the development and
in three years which is the time Horizon
we picked you can do I think at the
lowest you can do with BSL is four years
or the high longest duration you could
do something like every year it's like
your personal choice after three years
it becomes Apache licensed and a lot of
Open Source Advocates who are like well
like three years is a lifetime I'm like
that's cool we're not here to let other
people build businesses that Century so
I could care less about those arguments
right I want people to be able to run it
self-hosted because like I want
everybody to be able to use our software
I don't need people to be able to sell
it I don't need people to be able to
take it and do whatever they want with
it it's irrelevant like right to the
world but after three years all that
knowledge that we've gained in that
prior art becomes public domain right
and so we still achieve almost like this
knowledge share and you can it's still
Source you can view the source you can
like be inspired by it and it's software
it's like it's only so protected at the
end of the day and so that's what it is
for us right so it allows us to keep it
open source so like what is on
century.io again other than some
proprietary stuff that's like billing
code is literally like that Mainline
branch is what we're shipping to
production at the end of the day and I
mean that's cool like that that's like a
lot of the ways in the spirit of Open
Source but it doesn't pray for Humanity
to be like nice humans all the time
right like it protects the business and
the development in the you know tens to
hundreds of millions of dollars we
poured into like r d over the years
right it sounds like the decision you
made is probably very similar to other
vendors like and elastic trying to
think of some other examples I guess
cockroach is another yeah it is very
similar the difference is like
there's very few companies that operate
like Century in the world that are like
a SAS service that happens to be open
source most of those are like
infrastructure that you probably want to
run yourself and most of those they're
billing the way they make money is
actually still you running that software
yourself right and so they may not be
open course some of them are but there's
still a lot of it's fundamentally not a
cloud service that they're selling like
they will try but like if you're looking
at like elastic most people use it
because they can run it on Prem
otherwise I'm just going to use whatever
the Google check boxy button click thing
is at the end of the day but there are a
lot of people even the BSL model there's
a lot of people use it like cockroach is
one of the first that I recall that used
it and we were inspired and learned
about it from I could not tell you who
else uses it but it's become a more
popular thing and whether it's the right
solution or not there needs to be
something that is mainstream that people
use that achieves this that basically is
the BSL and hopefully it's a BSL or some
knockoff because the problem is if you
have 15 different flavors of this
license legal review is not fun and if
legal review is not fun it gets
blockchain companies right and so mango
is its own license elastic I think is
its own license they're both like
proprietary things that are one offset
have to go through a legal review BSL is
a known quantity with a clause so all
legal has to do is like review that
clause and say does this Clause Is that
safe enough for us or not right so it's
a very like simple decision at that
point and so I don't know hopefully the
industry figures that out instead of
constantly bickering about what is and
isn't open source because that would be
a much better spent of people's time
these days if you're building a new
product I mean when you look back at
Century you started with the BSD license
which is a very permissive license
what's the things you would look at to
decide that you're going to start this
new product with a permissive license
versus go straight to the BSL license
honestly I would just not get distracted
by that choice early on in a project I
think it depends on what you're building
in all honesty like if I were building
something that was designed it was like
infrastructure that was like so low
friction that you could just spin it up
and it worked like very well
Amazon's gonna sell that they're going
to take it they're gonna be like cool we
can spin this up for you too and then
they're gonna that mean you're gonna
struggle right like I think now is that
actually what would happen I don't know
but that's a risk right and I think this
was like the kind of risk people like
cockroach were worried about was like
Amazon might sell it because they saw
that like elastic that happened to them
now elastic is done fine nobody should
be sad for Alaska they've made plenty of
money with Amazon selling it on top like
it doesn't really matter right like pity
the executives there or something it
doesn't really matter but for a early
stage project it's so irrelevant like if
you make your license restricted you
will get less adoption so unless the
your open source project is only going
to be used by 100 companies in the world
having a restrictive license is only
going to harm you right and so you can
do it but I just wouldn't an open course
the same thing it's just like yeah I
don't know like this is the glory of SAS
it's like you can build an open source
thing and not care that it's open source
now because you can just sell a cloud
service and people will buy the cloud
service no matter what right like
centuries model when we raised our seed
funding was it was BSD license time
super free super open and people are
like well why would anybody pay for it
and I'm like it doesn't matter if they
don't pay for Century they won't pay for
anything in the industry because we will
build the best thing and it will be so
free and good that nobody will have a
choice like but to use it right and the
reality is if you're a reasonable
company you don't want to spend a bunch
of engineering hours and time and money
on running this random service that you
can just Outsource like that's true
forever everything in the world right
and that was the reality for a century
like I said there was no like actual
risk of the business it was just like
frankly it was just me off that I had
this one company that was constantly
trying to sell out and so I'm like you
know what this is my middle finger to
you is the BSL license and I can never
think about you again now but we were
already a successful business when that
came along like people already used the
SAS service not everybody but plenty of
people and so for me it was just like is
your goal that you want lots of
customers using your thing use a
permissive license otherwise you're like
over optimizing for a non-outcome that's
the same thing with like people that
they'll build like random open source
stuff and they use like GPL or something
it's almost like you want to put your
politics on another company like you
want to force them to contribute back
who cares they're either going to
contribute back or not like it's still
open source at the end of the day don't
like restrict people's usage if you're
just building like something on the side
and so like we actually have a policy
internally we won't license anything as
a GPL variant like it's just not
something we think is the right approach
to open source right again you can have
an opinion on it doesn't really matter
to us but we're like no if it's open
source if it's actually intended to be
like the free open source it should be
free without the constraints who cares
if somebody monetizes it like that's the
beauty of Open Source it's like it helps
everybody you know it's almost like a
charity to some degree so I'd say I have
a lot of strong opinions about it but
mostly is like don't distract yourself
with things that don't matters this is
like a broad statement for anything let
alone the open source licensing yeah
that makes sense I mean you don't know
that your product is going to get
adoption to begin with right so it's
probably you would take a path similar
to Sentry where you have something
permissive you see do people care is
this actually a business and then once
it becomes one then you can maybe worry
about licensing exactly yeah because you
can always change your license later or
you can find another thing to augment
the software you've built that allows
you to monetize it which is super common
like you see this like there's been a
lot of stuff that's raised funding
recently
core is still open source true free open
source and then they're like this is how
we're going to monetize development via
some mechanism like some cloud services
or something that's not true for
everybody you can't just take open
source and monetize it but like if
that's what you want to do why'd you
build open source in the first place
right like just save yourself a headache
like I think nginx I don't know how well
they've done as a business but like what
are you going to monetize in nginx it
already just works oh you got some like
Cloud analytics it's cool like maybe
they were useful I never use them but
like I'm not going to buy that but that
was just like oh nginx so successful
could we monetize it versus could we
build a business that actually is open
source one's like very intentional
versus you know capitalistic I would say
or predatory to some degree I'm not
talking about the nginx folks I love the
product in the business but you know
it's a much harder thing to do you love
the product but don't need to pay for it
exactly yeah I would probably still use
the product but these days that's more
of a commodity than anything like the
web server so so as we wrap up is there
anything else that you thought we should
have brought up
no I mean I think this was this was fun
you know I'm very much an authentic
person I think it's like I'm not a
marketer I like talking about things
that add value to folks lives not just
like pitching products and stuff so I
think it's good to go deeper on the
things which is fun I don't know since
she's doing a lot of cool stuff
hopefully people like it if you don't
tell us if you have issues tweet at me
we take every piece of feedback very
very seriously yeah
and if people want to see what you're up
to check out Sentry where should they
head century.io or get Sentry on Twitter
hopefully by the time this airs Twitter
so exists but yeah on a century.io
GitHub or get Sentry Sentry somewhere
you search for us you'll find us we're
very active on GitHub though so it's a
good form if you want to participate
that way David thank you so much for
coming on sophomore engineering radio
absolutely and thanks again for having
me this has been Jeremy Jung for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]
foreign